<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Sebastian Stier</title>
    <link>https://sebastianstier.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://sebastianstier.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://sebastianstier.com/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://sebastianstier.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Negative Campaigning in German elections: Measurement, Dynamics, and Determinants</title>
      <link>https://sebastianstier.com/project/negative-campaigning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sebastianstier.com/project/negative-campaigning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research on negative campaigning (NC), i.e. verbal attacks on political opponents, has gained considerable attention in recent years. Studies suggest that NC can have dysfunctional consequences for democracy (e.g. polarization, declining trust in politics). This applies in particular to negative campaign strategies that attack an opponent personally or in an uncivil manner. However, the causes and effects of NC have rarely been analyzed outside of the United States. This project, jointly led with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-koblenz-landau.de/de/landau/fb6/sowi/pw/abteilung/politische-kommunikation/team/Maier&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jürgen Maier&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-koblenz-landau.de/de/landau/fb8/ikms/kompsych/oschatz-corinna&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Corinna Oschatz&lt;/a&gt; (both University of Koblenz-Landau) investigates the determinants of the use of NC in German election campaigns at the federal and state level. The aim is to test explanatory factors at the micro level (politicians who use NC) and macro factors (structural conditions during election campaigns).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this purpose, we first use self-reports from candidate surveys to investigate the use and evaluation of NC by candidates. We draw on the candidate studies conducted as part of the German Longitudinal Election Study (GLES) for the 2013, 2017 and 2021 federal elections. In addition, we will invite all candidates of the relevant political parties who will take part in all of the 2021 &lt;em&gt;Landtag&lt;/em&gt; elections to a survey. In order to measure the actual use of NC, we collect the entire social media communication of candidates and hand code a high-quality training dataset that serves as the input for machine learning models for the detection of NC at a large scale. In contrast to established sources such as party manifestos, Twitter data is available at a more fine-grained level (of the individual candidate) and in larger numbers (hundreds of thousands of posts during an election campaign, in standardized form across parties). The results from the analysis of candidate surveys and social media will be linked on the level of individual candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the project makes an essential theoretical and empirical contribution towards a better understanding of the determinants of NC (1) over time, (2) at different federal levels and (3) depending on different individual characteristics of politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracking the effects of negative political communication during election campaigns in online and offline communication environments</title>
      <link>https://sebastianstier.com/project/web-track/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sebastianstier.com/project/web-track/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sebastianstier.com/files/webtrack_design.png&#34; alt=&#34;voters&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During election campaigns, many of the political messages citizens receive are negative – be it via strategic negative campaigning, media coverage or uncivil online conversations. Many studies in political communication and psychology have already focused on the effects of negativity on citizens’ reactions, e.g., attention and emotions, evaluation of politicians, or voting behavior. Most of these studies, however, investigated citizens’ political communication in isolation focusing on just one channel. Studies that focus on effects of negative information received from mass media as well as interpersonal communication environments online and offline (in the following MIC), are to the best of our knowledge non-existent – despite the obvious interactions in terms of processes and effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, most studies on negativity in campaigns either focus on traditional explanations of its effects on political outcomes through survey self-reports or they try to analyze the information processing of negative information, mostly within experimental designs. It has hardly been possible to observe the effects of negativity on fast-lived variables like attention and emotions in-situ and to analyze its effects on political outcomes in an integrated research design. As a consequence, the state of research regarding the overall impact of negative political communication on important political outcomes such as evaluation of political actors, voting behavior and affective polarization so far has been fairly inconclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, jointly led with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-koblenz-landau.de/de/landau/fb8/ikms/kompsych/mmaier&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michaela Maier&lt;/a&gt; (University of Koblenz-Landau) and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://lukasotto.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lukas Otto&lt;/a&gt; (Amsterdam School of Communication Research), we aim to comprehensively analyze the effects of negativity in MIC during election campaigns to make a fourfold contribution to the state of research: First, we examine the dynamic exposure of citizens to negative political communication in various communication environments during an election campaign. Thereby, investigating the different communication types in one research design also allows us to analyze the reciprocal relations between mediated and interpersonal communication online and offline. Second, we analyze the short-term effects of negative contents on attentional and emotional processing, and third, longer-term effects on political outcomes. By taking a longitudinal perspective, we conceptualize and measure exposure to and effects of negativity during campaigns as dynamic processes. Fourth, we methodologically contribute to the state of research by using an innovative methodology that allows us to observe the aforementioned processes in a real-world setting: we combine approaches of offline and online tracking to continuously observe citizens&#39; engagement in political communication, surveys to assess their short-term and long-term reactions, and automated content analysis to link participants&#39; reactions to concrete communication contents. The study will be conducted during the hot phase of the German federal election campaign in September 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What do &#39;the people&#39; want? Digital Media and Populism in Europe and the U.S.</title>
      <link>https://sebastianstier.com/project/online-populism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sebastianstier.com/project/online-populism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sebastianstier.com/files/voters.png&#34; alt=&#34;voters&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars highlight several mechanisms of how digital media might benefit populists: (1) populist parties use digital media to bypass media gatekeepers that tend to obfuscate and filter their populist message; (2) social network sites such as Facebook and Twitter open up direct channels of communication between populist parties and voters/supporters, thereby bringing to life a core promise of the populist worldview; (3) social media are conducive to the spread of misinformation and disinformation that are core components in the communication strategies of populist parties; and (4) mainstream media amplify populist actors&#39; online contents as they are reliable providers of scandals and have a massive news value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with the other two PIs 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencespo.fr/centre-etudes-europeennes/en/researcher/caterina-froio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Caterina Froio&lt;/a&gt; (Sciences Po, Paris) and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/people/ralph-schroeder&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ralph Schroeder&lt;/a&gt; (University of Oxford) and our respective teams, I test these theories using web browsing histories and multiple survey waves that were collected with the informed consent of more than 8,000 study participants in six countries. In addition, we collected the social media posts of a large sample of politicians and parties on Facebook and Twitter and conducted conjoint experiments. The research period captures the three months preceding the European Parliament (EP) election 2019 in six countries: France, Germany, Italy, Spain, the UK and the U.S., which is the reference case in much of political communication research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
